Bertie H. Clinkscales Papers
Bertie H. Clinkscales Papers
1941-1964
Clinkscales, Bertie H.
0.5 linear ft.
Award-winning poet, writer, State Historian for the United Daughters of the Confederacy (UDC) South Carolina Division, and SU alumna. Collection includes correspondence, manuscripts, published materials, subject files, clippings, and memorabilia.
2744141
Biographical History
Bertie Hix Clinkscales (1888-1976), also referred to as Mrs. C. C. Clinkscales, was an American poet and writer.
Clinkscales was born on February 24, 1888 in Georgia to Isaac Rosser Hix and Mattie L. Vandiver Hix, but became a devoted and lifelong resident of Greenville, South Carolina. She graduated from Syracuse University, and became an award-wining writer and poet who was published in several magazines. South Carolina Magazine regularly published her work. Apart from writing, Clinkscales held several chair positions in the South Carolina Federation of Women's Clubs and other notable organizations, including many active and prominent appointments over the course of her life in the United Daughters of the Confederacy (UDC) South Carolina Division.
Clinkscales and her husband, Cleon Curtis Clinkscales Sr. (1881-1961), had one son, Cleon C. Clinkscales Jr. (1910-1948), who died at the age of 38. Bertie Clinkscales died on July 25, 1976.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bertie H. Clinkscales Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Though Clinkscales was acquainted with many important people in the literary world, including publishers and other affiliated organizations, very little is found in the Correspondence. The majority of the letters have no more than personal significance, such as exchanges between lifelong friends and peers between 1948-1964. Some adjacent correspondence items, specifically invitations, newspaper clippings, and award notifications, have been filed under Memorabilia.
Memorabilia relates to the driving interests in Clinkscales' life in Greenville, South Carolina. Her frequent publications in local outlets and attendance at both professional and social events are exemplified, as well as her continuing involvement in the United Daughters of the Confederacy (UDC) and numerous women's clubs. These materials encompass award receipts, newspaper clippings, formal event invitations, pamphlets, yearbooks, photographs, programs, women's clubs brochures, and official documents of the UDC. Clippings contains articles that were evidently meaningful to Clinkscales on a personal level, including events, people, and groups she was affiliated with. Clippings pertaining to her writings are filed with the relevant publication in the next series.
Writings is divided into two subseries: Manuscripts and Published Materials. Manuscripts contains typescript materials and those in her own handwriting, subdivided into poems and prose. Manuscripts are almost entirely undated. Published materials include articles, essays, books, etc. A few complete issues of magazines offer established dates for some of her published articles, most articles are in the form of clippings and do not provide information on date or source of publication. Clinkscales' prose focuses on life in the South and Southerners in general, mostly regarding South Carolina. These include several profiles of distinguished southerners, as well as items on the Confederacy, women in the South, Southern churches of note, and appearances or contributive works to several women's councils in South Carolina. Poems often allude to more universal topics such as weather, nature, seasons, holidays, religion, and memory. Little of Clinkscales' work mentions personal or familial relations.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent; those with only a first name or no name at all are filed at the end. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by folder title (or topic). Writings are divided into subseries: Manuscripts and Published Materials. Each subseries is further divided into poems or prose and then arranged in alphabetical order by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Clinkscales, Bertie H.; United Daughters of the Confederacy.; The far horizons -- Clinkscales, Bertie H.; Poets, American.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; South Carolina (state); Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival an manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bertie Clinkscales, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - A-Z, 1948-1964; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - First name only (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, clippings about; announcements of (Box 1)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Furman University Bulletin, 1950; 1963; 2 issues (Box 1)
  - Event invitations (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1949; formal portrait, and a candid shot posing with a cup she won for an essay (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1947-1954; includes church services and meetings of the South Carolina Federation of Women's Clubs (Box 1)
  - South Carolina Columbian, 1957; includes news items by and about Clinkscales; 4 issues (Box 1)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy (UDC), mostly clippings about the organization and/or Clinkscales' involvement (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1941; 1948-1949,; 1958,; 1963; garden clubs, women's clubs, etc.; at least one is dedicated to Clinkscales for her service (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts
    - Poems, undated; mostly typescripts, some with corrections (Box 1)
    - Prose, undated; mostly typescripts, some with corrections (Box 1)
  - Published materials
    - Poetry collection, The Far Horizon, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Poems, circa 1945-1964; includes both clippings and a few complete issues of various magazines; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Prose, circa 1951-1963; includes both clippings and a few complete issues of various magazines; 2 folders (Box 2)